<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-avtcore-cc-feedback-message-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Congestion Control Feedback in RTCP">RTP Control Protocol
    (RTCP) Feedback for Congestion Control</title>

    <author fullname="Zaheduzzaman Sarker" initials="Z." surname="Sarker">
      <organization>Ericsson AB</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Luleae</city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+46107173743</phone>

        <email>zaheduzzaman.sarker@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Colin Perkins" initials="C. S." surname="Perkins">
      <organization>University of Glasgow</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>School of Computing Science</street>

          <city>Glasgow</city>

          <code>G12 8QQ</code>

          <country>United Kingdom</country>
        </postal>

        <email>csp@csperkins.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Varun Singh" initials="V." surname="Singh">
      <organization abbrev="callstats.io">Nemu Dialogue Systems
      Oy</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Runeberginkatu 4c A 4</street>

          <city>Helsinki</city>

          <code>00100</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>varun.singh@iki.fi</email>

        <uri>http://www.callstats.io/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Michael A. Ramalho" initials="M. A." surname="Ramalho">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco Systems">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6310 Watercrest Way Unit 203</street>

          <city>Lakewood Ranch</city>

          <region>FL</region>

          <code>34202</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 919 476 2038</phone>

        <email>mramalho@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="2" month="March" year="2018" />

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>IETF RMCAT Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>Congestion control, feedback message, RTP, RTCP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes an RTCP feedback message intended to enable
      congestion control for interactive real-time traffic using RTP. The
      feedback message is designed for use with a sender-based congestion
      control algorithm, in which the receiver of an RTP flow sends RTCP
      feedback packets to the sender containing the information the sender
      needs to perform congestion control.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>For interactive real-time traffic, such as video conferencing
      flows, the typical protocol choice is the Real-time Transport
      Protocol (RTP) running over the User Datagram Protocol (UDP). RTP
      does not provide any guarantee of Quality of Service (QoS), reliability,
      or timely delivery, and expects the underlying transport protocol to
      do so.  UDP alone certainly does not meet that expectation. However,
      the RTP Control Protocol (RTCP) provides a mechanism by which the
      receiver of an RTP flow can periodically send transport and media
      quality metrics to the sender of that RTP flow. This information can
      be used by the sender to perform congestion control.  In the absence
      of standardized messages for this purpose, designers of congestion
      control algorithms have developed proprietary RTCP messages that
      convey only those parameters needed for their respective designs.
      As a direct result, the different congestion control (i.e., rate
      adaptation) designs are not interoperable.  To enable algorithm
      evolution as well as interoperability across designs (e.g., different
      rate adaptation algorithms), it is highly desirable to have generic
      congestion control feedback format.</t>

      <t>To help achieve interoperability for unicast RTP congestion control,
      this memo proposes a common RTCP feedback packet format that can be used by
      NADA <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-nada"></xref>, SCReAM <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-scream-cc"></xref>, Google Congestion Control
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-gcc"></xref> and Shared Bottleneck
      Detection <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-sbd"></xref>, and hopefully
      also by future RTP congestion control algorithms.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>In addition the terminology defined in <xref
      target="RFC3550"></xref>, <xref target="RFC3551"></xref>, <xref
      target="RFC3611"></xref>, <xref target="RFC4585"></xref>, and <xref
      target="RFC5506"></xref> applies.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="feedback_message" title="RTCP Feedback for Congestion Control">
      <t>Based on an analysis of NADA <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-nada"></xref>,
      SCReAM <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-scream-cc"></xref>, Google
      Congestion Control <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-gcc"></xref> and
      Shared Bottleneck Detection <xref target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-sbd"></xref>,
      the following per-RTP packet congestion control feedback information
      has been determined to be necessary:</t>

      <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>RTP sequence number: The receiver of an RTP flow needs to feedback
          the sequence numbers of the received RTP packets to the sender, so the
          sender can determine which packets were received and which were lost.
          Packet loss is used as an indication of congestion by many congestion
          control algorithms.</t>

          <t>Packet Arrival Time: The receiver of an RTP flow needs to feedback
          the arrival time of each RTP packet to the sender. Packet delay and/or
          delay variation (jitter) is used as a congestion signal by some congestion
          control algorithms.</t>

          <t>Packet Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) Marking: If ECN
          <xref target="RFC3168"></xref>, <xref target="RFC6679"></xref> is
          used, it is necessary to feedback the 2-bit ECN mark in received
          RTP packets, indicating for each RTP packet whether it is marked
          not-ECT, ECT(0), ECT(1), or ECN-CE. If the path used by the RTP
          traffic is ECN capable the sender can use Congestion Experienced
          (ECN-CE) marking information as a congestion control signal.</t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>Every RTP flow is identified by its Synchronization Source (SSRC)
      identifier. Accordingly, the RTCP feedback format needs to group its
      reports by SSRC, sending one report block per received SSRC.</t>

      <t>As a practical matter, we note that host operating system (OS)
      process interruptions can occur at inopportune times. Accordingly,
      recording RTP packet send times at the sender, and the corresponding
      RTP packet arrival times at the
      receiver, needs to be done with deliberate care. This is because the time
      duration of host OS interruptions can be significant relative to the
      precision desired in the one-way delay estimates. Specifically, the send
      time needs to be recorded at the last opportunity prior to transmitting
      the RTP packet at the sender, and the arrival time at the receiver needs
      to be recorded at the earliest available opportunity.</t>

      <section anchor="sec:ccfb" title="RTCP Congestion Control Feedback Report">
        <t>Congestion control feedback can be sent as part of a regular
        scheduled RTCP report, or in an RTP/AVPF early feedback packet. 
        If sent as early feedback, congestion control feedback MAY be 
        sent in a non-compound RTCP packet <xref target="RFC5506"></xref> 
        if the RTP/AVPF profile <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> or the 
        RTP/SAVPF profile <xref target="RFC5124"></xref> is used.</t>

        <t>Irrespective of how it is transported, the congestion control 
        feedback is sent as a Transport Layer Feedback Message (RTCP packet 
        type 205). The format of this RTCP packet is as follows:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |V=2|P| FMT=CCFB |   PT = 205   |          length               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                 SSRC of RTCP packet sender                    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                   SSRC of 1st RTP Stream                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |          begin_seq            |             end_seq           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |L|ECN|  Arrival time offset    | ...                           .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                   SSRC of nth RTP Stream                      |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |          begin_seq            |             end_seq           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |L|ECN|  Arrival time offset    | ...                           |
    .                                                               .
    .                                                               .
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                 Report Timestamp (32bits)                     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The first eight octets comprise a standard RTCP header, with
        PT=205 and FMT=CCFB indicating that this is a congestion control
        feedback packet, and with the SSRC set to that of the sender of
        the RTCP packet. (NOTE TO RFC EDITOR: please replace CCFB here and
        in the above diagram with the IANA assigned RTCP feedback packet
        type, and remove this note)</t>

        <t>Section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC4585"></xref> requires the RTCP
        header to be followed by the SSRC of the RTP flow being reported 
        upon.  Accordingly, the RTCP header is followed by a report block
        for each SSRC from which RTP packets have been received, followed
        by a Report Timestamp.</t>
     
        <t>Each report block begins with the SSRC of the received RTP Stream
        on which it is reporting. Following this, each sequence number between
        the begin_seq and end_seq (both inclusive) is represented by a packet
        metric block of 16-bits that contains the L, ECN, and ATO fields. If
        an odd number of reports are included, i.e., end_seq - begin_seq is
        an odd number, then 16 bits of zero padding MUST be added after the
        last report, to align the RTCP packet to a four (4) bytes boundary.
        The L, ECN, and ATO fields are as follows:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              L (1 bit): is a boolean to indicate if the packet was
              received. 0 represents that the packet was not yet received
              and all the subsequent bits (ECN and ATO) are also set to 0.
              1 represent the packet was received and the subsequent bits
              in the block need to be parsed.
            </t>

            <t>
              ECN (2 bits): is the echoed ECN mark of the packet. These 
              are set to 00 if not received, or if ECN is not used.
            </t>

            <t>
              Arrival time offset (ATO, 13 bits): is the relative arrival
              time of the RTP packets at the receiver before this feedback
              report was generated measured in milliseconds. It is
              calculated by subtracting the reception timestamp of the RTP
              packet denoted by this 16bit block and the timestamp (RTS) of
              this report.  If the measured value is greater than 8.189
              seconds (the value that would be coded as 0x1FFD), the value
              0x1FFE MUST be reported to indicate an over-range positive
              measurement.  If the measurement is unavailable, the value
              0x1FFF MUST be reported.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>The RTCP packet concludes with the Report Timestamp (RTS, 32 bits).
        This represents the time instant when the RTCP report was generated.
        The sender of the feedback message decides on the wall-clock. Usually,
        it should be derived from the same wall-clock that is used for
        timestamping RTP packets arrival . Consistency in the unit and
        resolution (10th of millisecond should be good enough ) is important
        here. In addition, the RTP sender can ask for a specific resolution
        it wants.</t>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Feedback Frequency and Overhead">
      <t>There is a trade-off between speed and accuracy of reporting, and the
      overhead of the reports. <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-rtp-cc-feedback"></xref> discusses this
      trade-off, and the possible rates of feedback.</t>

      <t>It is a general understanding that the congestion control algorithms
      will work better with more frequent feedback - per packet feedback.
      However, RTCP bandwidth and transmission rules put some upper limits on
      how frequently the RTCP feedback messages can be send from the RTP
      receiver to the RTP sender. It has been shown <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-rmcat-rtp-cc-feedback"></xref> that in most cases a per
      frame feedback is a reasonable assumption on how frequent the RTCP
      feedback messages can be transmitted. The design team also have noted
      that even if a higher frequency of feedback is desired it is not viable
      if the feedback messages starts to compete against the RTP traffic on
      the feedback path during congestion period. Analyzing the feedback
      interval requirement <xref target="feedback-requirements"></xref> it can
      be seen that the candidate algorithms can perform with a feedback
      interval range of 50-200ms. A value within this range need to be
      negotiated at session setup.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Design Rationale">
      <t>The primary function of RTCP Sender Report (SR) / Receiver Report
      (RR) is to report the reception quality of the RTP packets. The regular SR / RR
      reports contain information about observed jitter, fractional packet
      loss and cumulative packet loss. The original intent of this information
      was to assist flow and congestion control mechanisms. Even though it is
      possible to do congestion control based on information provided in the
      SR/RR reports it is not sufficient to design an efficient congestion
      control algorithm for interactive real-time communication. An efficient
      congestion control algorithm requires more fine grain information on per
      packet (see <xref target="feedback_message"></xref>) to react to the
      congestion or to avoid funder congestion on the path.</t>

      <t>Codec Control Message for AVPF <xref target="RFC5104"></xref> defines
      Temporary Maximum Media Bit Rate (TMMBR) message which conveys a
      temporary maximum bitrate limitation from the receiver of the RTP packets to
      the sender of the RTP packets. Even though it is not designed to replace
      congestion control, TMMBR has been used as a means to do receiver based
      congestion control where the session bandwidth is high enough to send
      frequent TMMBR messages especially with reduced sized reports <xref
      target="RFC5506"></xref>. This requires the receiver of the RTP packets to
      analyze the data reception, detect congestion level and recommend a
      maximum bitrate suitable for current available bandwidth on the path
      with an assumption that the sender of the RTP packets always honors the TMMBR
      message. This requirement is completely opposite of the sender based
      congestion control approach. Hence, TMMBR cannot be as a signaling means
      for a sender based congestion control mechanism. However, TMMBR should
      be viewed a complimentary signaling mechanism to establish receiver's
      current view of acceptable maximum bitrate which a sender based
      congestion control should honor.</t>

      <t>There are number of RTCP eXtended Report (XR) blocks have been
      defined for reporting of delay, loss and ECN marking. It is possible to
      combine several XR blocks to report the loss and ECN marking at the cost
      of overhead and complexity. However, there is no existing RTCP XR block
      to report packet arrival time.</t>

      <t>Considering the issues discussed here it is rational to design a new
      congestion control feedback signaling mechanism for sender based
      congestion control algorithm.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>This document is an outcome of RMCAT design team discussion. We would
      like to thank all participants specially Xiaoquing Zhu, Stefan Holmer,
      David, Ingemar Johansson and Randell Jesup for their valuable
      contribution to the discussions and to the document.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>IANA is requested to assign a new value in the "FMT Values for RTPFB 
        Payload Types" registry for the CCFB transport layer feedback packet
        described in <xref target="sec:ccfb"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>There is a risk of causing congestion if an on-path attacker modifies
      the feedback messages in such a manner to make available bandwidth
      greater than it is in reality. [More on security consideration TBD.]</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3550'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3551'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3611'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4585'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5124'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5506'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3168'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6679'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rmcat-rtp-cc-feedback'?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rmcat-nada'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rmcat-scream-cc"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rmcat-gcc"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-rmcat-sbd"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5104'?>

      <reference anchor="feedback-requirements"
                 target="://www.ietf.org/proceedings/95/slides/slides-95-rmcat-1.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>RMCAT Feedback Requirements</title>

          <author>
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
